To put it simply, it's about the connections you make.
简单点说就是拉的关系
But rather than just connections,
与其说是拉的关系
it's more about the useful people you network with.
不如说是你结交的有用之人啊
There's a rather pragmatic saying
常说有一种非常功利的说法
about making friends
叫做交朋友
that you should only befriend those who are useful
要交有用的
but if you approach friendships with this mindset
但如果你抱着这种心态
generally speaking
通常来讲
you might end up with superficial connections
最后交的可能反而是无效社交
yet we emphasize the importance of socializing
但我们说了社交的重要性呢
especially in business where networking is crucial
其实他在做生意有圈层
and for ordinary folks like us
平时作为一个普通小老百姓来讲的话
Even if you don’t do business
你即使不做生意
or step into the commercial world
不迈上商业领域
social currency is still very important to me
其实社交货币对我来讲也非常重要
I recently read a book called The Social Economy
我最近读了一本叫社交经济的书
The author of The Social Economy is from the former Soviet Union
肖经济书就是他这个作者是前苏联的
and later immigrated to the United States
后来才移民到美国
He mentioned that when his mother was alive
他就说他母亲在世的时候呢
it was often the case that the Soviet Union had a system of rationing
经常那时候苏联的物物资配给制
but this was during the 1970s and 1980s
但是他在七八十年代的时候
Life at home is quite comfortable
家里过得很爽
Because his mother is a doctor
因为他的母亲是个医生啊
She often provides free medical consultations
经常给别人义诊
So these things form part of social currency
所以这种东西是社交货币的构成
Let's start with social currency
我们首先说社交货币
First, you need to have something to trade as social currency For example, you might be a hard asset You know how to build computers You can help people with medical issues You'd be the one to fight legal battles for others. You're like the lawyer I'm actually using right now.
你首先要有兑换社交货币的东西 比如你就硬通货 你会装电脑啊 你会给别人那个看病啊 你会给别人打官司 你就像我其实在我现在用的这个律师啊
Including the doctor I'm seeing currently.
包括我现在找的医生
Most of them I found through social networks.
大部分都是我通过啊这个社交网络
People I met on social media, who are my followers.
社交媒体以后认识的人就是我的粉丝啊
Thinking back to the life my parents provided for me,
早年间我想我爸我妈给我的生活来讲
A lot of the time, it was my dad,
很多的时候都是我爸啊
Or my mom, who saved up these resources,
或者我妈他们这个积攒下来的
These social connections, if you will.
这个社交的这些东西来讲
Give me one to use
给我一使用的
Back in the old days, many things weren’t as readily available
就想早年间很多东西来讲啊
Material exchange wasn’t as developed
物资交换并不是那么发达
Often, even if you had money
很多的时候即使你用钱
You couldn’t get the resources the other party wanted
也没有办法取得对方想用的这些资源
More often, it was about mutual benefit
更多来讲是一讲一种互惠互利啊
Like my dad, back in the day, he worked at a gallery
你像我爸早年间他在画廊
He helped many artists sell their paintings
他就帮助很多画家卖画
Because artists, as a type of creator
因为画家作为一种艺术家
So very aloof.
非常的清高啊
For these people,
而这些人来讲的话
they also rely on the income from selling paintings to live.
又依靠这些卖画的收入生活
So he formed a life-and-death alliance with them.
所以他跟他们就结成一种生死同盟的关系
My mom, as an accountant at an accounting firm,
我妈作为会计师事务所的会计啊
often helps various companies handle their financial records. When it comes to financial records, it’s also a matter of life and death. So gradually, a kind of relationship developed, one that is both close and distant with entrepreneurs and artists, a very harmonious relationship.
经常帮各个公司处理他们的账务 所以来讲的话账务这些东西来讲 那也是生死攸关的事情 所以慢慢就形成了一种跟企业家 跟艺术家的这么一种若即若离 的一种非常和谐的一种关系
In this dynamic,
所以在但其中来讲
reflecting on my past,
我回想我过去啊
whether it was applying to school,
人生不管是从这个学校的报考啊
things at home,
这家里的东西啊
mobile phones,
手机啊
cameras
摄像机啊
Basically, they are all new.
基本来讲就都是新的
Someone will regularly deliver these items.
会有人定期会送这些东西
These items are essentially what we call social currency.
就这些东西其实就是所谓的社交货币
They represent the convenience you can offer to others.
就是你能给别人提供的便利
Or the leverage you have over others.
或者你掌握别人的命脉
You accumulate these things in your daily life.
就这些东西你平时呢积攒这些东西
For the future development of your children,
对于你将来子女的发展
For your own lifestyle,
对你自己的生活方式来讲来讲
They all contribute to a richer and more fulfilling experience.
丰富程度都是有好处的
Many things aren't necessarily bought with money.
很多东西未必真的是从金钱换来的
That's why we often say making friends.
所以我们常说交朋友
Actually, when you have a lot of private connections in your social network,
其实这社交网络你的私域流量很多的时候
you can manage and categorize them.
你加以运营加以分类
For example, I now have over 20,000 WeChat friends.
就像我现在有2万多微信好友了
Speaking of these WeChat friends,
这些微信好友来讲
they are spread all over the world.
遍布世界各地啊
And in terms of these connections,
这些边来讲
they come from various industries and circles.
这又又是各个行业各个圈层
Let's talk about the simplest issue.
咱们说个最简单的问题
You always want to meet young girls and add them on WeChat, right? Isn't that also something you get from your social network? So, when it comes to social networks nowadays, how to expand your connections, increase your circle of friends, not just classmates,
你一层总想认识小妹妹加薇薇 不是也是从你的社交网络中得来的吗 所以说我们现在社交网络来讲 如何扩大自己的扩列 增加自己的朋友圈 不再是同学
not just colleagues,
不再是同事
not just people you meet at clubs.
不再是一些啊俱乐部认识的这些人
How do you usually get to know others?
你平时该怎么样认识别人
To achieve a deep and effective social connection,
达成一个深度有效社交
I think it's actually a good idea to create your own online presence,
那我想其实你在网上做一个自己的号
build your own social media platform,
做一个自己的社交媒体
which can be very useful,
是一个非常有用的
a very suitable way to earn social capital.
非常合适的一种社交货币的获取方法
That is, once you truly gain social capital,
也就是说真正你获得了社交货币以后
many opportunities will arise,
很多东西啊
we often talk about business insights and more, and when exactly they come into play.
我们说生意经更多的东西到底什么时候
These trends may come
这些风口到来
You never know when these things will actually be useful to you
什么时候这些东西对你真正有用的时候
But your friend might catch them first
你是不知道的
So you, how should I put it
但是你的朋友可能先捕捉到
You're like an intelligence officer
所以你就像你一个怎么说呢
Who needs to build a vast intelligence network
就像情报人员一样
To ensure you get this information
他要这支罗一个非常大的一个情报网
To get it as soon as possible
能够保证他得到这些东西
Being able to get these things right away
能够第一时间就得到这些东西
So it's like fishing.
所以这就好像你捕鱼一样
Fishing and angling.
捕鱼跟钓鱼
In daily life, you usually interact with just one or two people.
你平时人你只接触一两个人
That's angling.
这就是钓鱼
If you have a robust social network,
如果你有一个强强大的社交网络
and you frequently maintain this network, then that's fishing. Back then, they used gill nets for fishing. Mechanized fishing, that's incredibly fast. So, in today's world, regardless of the tools we use or how we do it, we need to strengthen our network expansion.
你经常去维护这个网络来讲 那就是捕鱼啊 那时候用刺网捕鱼啊 机械化捕鱼 那就是非常快的 所以来讲在今天的世界当中来讲 我们不论用到哪种工具还是怎么样 就要强大的帮我们去扩交啊
Expand the vertical and horizontal links of our social network,
扩大我们社交网络这个纵向跟横向的这个链
whether it's with people of the same age or in the same industry,
不管是你同年龄段的还是同行业的
intergenerational connections are crucial.
不同年龄段的这个东西非常重要
So, acquiring social capital is vital for our life journey,
所以社交货币的取得对于我们人生的旅程来讲
extremely important.
非常的重要